<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3315 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-cfkss-dhc-relay-dhcp4-over-dhcp6-00"
     updates="3315" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Relay DHCPv4 over DHCPv6">Relay DHCPv4 messages
    over DHCPv6</title>

    <author fullname="Marcin Siodelski" initials="M." surname="Siodelski">
      <organization abbrev="ISC"></organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter Street</street>
          <city>Redwood City</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94063</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 650 423 1431</phone>
        <email>msiodelski@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Dynamic Host Configuration Working Group</workgroup>


    <keyword>DHCPv4</keyword>
    <keyword>DHCPv6</keyword>
    <keyword>DHCPv4 over DHCPv6</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the mechanism to provision the DHCPv4
      services over the DHCPv6 protocol.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>During the transition from IPv4 to IPv6 the dual stack networks
      are common. In such networks either DHCPv4 or DHCPv6 servers are used
      by hosts to obtain configuration. In many cases, the host being configured
      with DHCPv4 protocol is separated from the DHCPv4 server by the IPv6 only
      network segment, while existing protocols to not allow for DHCPv4 to
      traverse IPv6 network.</t>
      <t>This document describes extensions to DHCPv6 protocol to allow
      transmission of DHCPv4 traffic via DHCPv6 enabled network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Use Cases">
      <t>The assumption that DHCPv4 packets can be encapsulated by the DHCPv6
      RELAY-FORWARD and RELAY-REPLY messages is fundamental for the extensions
      described in this document. Thus, if the DHCP4 client is separated from
      the DHCP4 server by the IPv6 network segment it is required that DHCP6
      traffic is carried through this segment and that at least one relay agent
      resides on the route between the DHCP4 client and server.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="overview-dhcp6-server"
              title="Network topology with DHCPv6 server handling
                     DHCPv4 messages">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
+--------------+   v4
| DHCP4 client |--------+
+--------------+        |    +-------+   Relayed  +---------------+
                        +----| Relay |------------| DHCPv6 server |
+--------------+   v6   |    +-------+  v4 and v6 +---------------+
| DHCP6 client |--------+
+--------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The <xref target="overview-dhcp6-server"/> shows the sample network
      topology where the traffic from both DHCP4 and DHCP6 clients is directed
      to the same DHCP6 server. The relay agent conveys both v4 or v6
      messages in RELAY-FORW message described in section 7.1 of
      <xref target="RFC3315">RFC 3315</xref>, but in two different options.
      The v6 messages are conveyed in OPTION_RELAY_MSG as described in the
      <xref target="RFC3315">RFC 3315</xref> while the v4 messages are conveyed in the
      new option OPTION_DHCP4_RELAY_MSG defined in this document. This
      guarantees that relay agents and servers may easely differentiate the v4
      and v6 traffic by simply looking at the type of the option being carried
      in the RELAY-FORW message.</t>

      <t>Once the server has processed the message it sends back the response to
      the relay agent in the RELAY-REPL message described in section 7.2 of
      <xref target="RFC3315">RFC 3315</xref>.</t>

      <t>The topology presented above requires that not only is DHCP6 server
      capable to process DHCP6, but also DHCP4 traffic. Such hybrid
      implementations are common and in many cases can be created with a minimal
      effort if the particular code comprises shared libraries with DHCP4 and
      DHCP6 packets processing logic.</t>

      <t>Another desired use case is to process the v4 and v6 messages on two
      distinct servers - DHCP6 server processing only v6 messages and the DHCP4
      server processing only v4 messagess. The corresponding network topology
      has been shown on the <xref target="overview-dhcp4-and-dhcp6-server"/>.
      </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="overview-dhcp4-and-dhcp6-server"
              title="Network topology with DHCPv6 server handling
                     DHCPv4 messages">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
                                            +--------------+
+--------------+  v4          +------------ | DHCP6 server |
| DHCP4 client |----+         |             +--------------+
+--------------+    |    +----+----+   +---------+   +--------------+
                    +----| Relay 1 |---| Relay 2 |---| DHCP4 server |
                         +----+----+   +---------+   +--------------+
+--------------+  v6          |
| DHCP6 client |--------------+
+--------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The v4 message is initiated by the DHCP4 client and is relayed by
      the Relay 1 in the same way as in the previous example. However, in this
      case the v6 and v4 messages are directed to different destinations.
      Relay 2 receives relayed v4 messages over IPv6 and relays them to the
      DHCP4 server using IPv4. Therefore, the following conditions MUST be
      met if the implementation supports this use case.
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>The relay agents MUST be configurable so as respective destinations
        can be specified for v4 and v6 traffic.</t>
        <t>The relay agent adjacent to the DHCP4 server MUST be able to
        relay incoming DHCP4o6 messages using IPv4.</t>
        <t>The relay agent adjacent to the DHCP4 server MUST be able to
        receive relayed DHCP4 traffic from the server and relay it using
        DHCPv6 RELAY-REPL as described above.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>The former of the use cases described in this chapter MUST be supported
      by all implementations conforming to this specification. The support for
      the latter use case is optional.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3315;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
