<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc autobreaks="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2131 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2131.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3315 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
]>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-XXX-dhc-dhcpv4-over-dhcpv6-00" ipr="trust200902">

<front>
  <title abbrev="DHCPv4 over DHCPv6">DHCPv4 over DHCPv6 Transport</title>
   <author></author>
<!-- Leave author list blank -->


  <date year="2013"/>

  <abstract>
    <t>This document describes a mechanism for obtaining IPv4 parameters
    in IPv6 networks by carrying DHCPv4 messages over DHCPv6 transport.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>As the migration to IPv6 continues to happen, IPv6 only networks
      will become more prevalent, and there will be a need to provide IPv4
      as a service over these IPv6 only networks. Along with the ability
      to provide IPv4 addressing, there might also be a need to provide
      other IPv4 configuration parameters such as addresses for reaching
      IPv4 services. There are several approaches possible to provision
      such information and this document describes one such approach.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Architecture Overview">
    <t>The architecture described in this document addresses the typical
    use case, where the DHCP client's uplink support IPv6 only and the
    Service Provider's network support IPv6 and limited IPv4 services which
    need to be accessed by the client over IPv6 only network.</t>

    <t>The DHCP clients can be running on CPE devices or end hosts, etc.
    At the time this document is written, DHCP clients on CPE devices are
    relatively easier to be modified comparing to those on end hosts. So this
    document takes the CPE as an example for describing the mechanism.
    This doesn't preclude end hosts from implementing the mechanism in the
    future. </t>

    <t>This mechanism works by carrying encapsulated DHCPv4 messages over
    DHCPv6 messages. One possible architecture detailing the usage of this
    mechanism is illustrated in the <xref target="architecture-overview"/>.
    In this architecture, the client is a DHCP client which can send and
    receive DHCPv4 message through a new type of DHCPv6 option, which is
    called DHCPv4 Message option. The format of the option is described in
    section 2. The client sends all its DHCPv6 packets, including the DHCPv4
    over DHCPv6 packets, to the well-known All_DHCP_Relay_Agents_and_Servers
    multicast address on the DHCPv6 server port 547.</t>

    <t>The DHCPv6 packet can be transmitted either via Relay Agents or
    directly to the server. The server is referred in this document as
    "Unified Server" for its capability of processing regular DHCPv6
    traffic as well as DHCPv4 packets wrapped in the DHCPv4 Message
    Option. Server replies with a relevant DHCPv6 packet carrying
    DHCPv4 response wrapped with the DHCPv4 Message Option. The Client
    receives response on the port 546.
    </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="architecture-overview"
              title="Architecture Overview">
      <artwork><![CDATA[
           _____________             _____________
          /             \           /             \
          |             |           |             |
 +--------+-+  IPv6   +-+-----------+-+  IPv6   +-+--------+
 |   DHCP   | network |     DHCP      | network | Unified  |
 |  Client  +---------+  Relay Agent  +---------+  Server  |
 | (on CPE) |         |               |         |          |
 +--------+-+         +-+-----------+-+         +-+--------+
          |             |           |             |
          \_____________/           \_____________/

      ]]></artwork>
    </figure>
    </section>


    <section title="DHCPv4 Message Option Format">
    <t>The DHCPv4 Message option carries a DHCPv4 message that is sent
    by the client or the server. Such DHCPv4 messages exclude any IP or
    UDP headers.</t>
    <t>The format of the DHCPv4 Message Option is:</t>
    <figure align="center" anchor="option-dhcpv4-msg"
            title="DHCPv4 Message Option Format">
    <artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_DHCPV4_MSG      |           option-len          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                         DHCPv4-message                        .
.                                                               .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

   option-code    OPTION_DHCPV4_MSG (TBD)

   option-len     Length of DHCPv4-message

   DHCPv4-message The DHCPv4 message sent by the client or the server

    ]]></artwork>
    </figure>
  </section>
<!--
  <section title="Method 1: DHCPv4 over DHCPv6">
    <section title="Method Overview">
      <t>In this method, DHCP client will put DHCPv4 message into a
      DHCPv6 option, i.e. the DHCPv4 Message Option. The DHCP packets
      will be sent out as a DHCPv6 message.</t>
    </section>
-->
    <section title="Client Behavior">
      <t>The DHCPv4 messages, including DHCPDISCOVER, DHCPOFFER, DHCPREQUEST,
      DHCPACK, etc, are conveyed in a newly defined DHCPv6 option mentioned
      in the former part. When the DHCP client requires an IPv4 address,
      it MUST generate a DHCPv4 message to apply one from DHCP server.
      The DHCPv4 message is wrapped in the DHCPv4 Message Option, which is
      then put into the Option field of DHCPv6 message. Client MUST store
      exactly one DHCPv4 Message Option in a single DHCPv6 message. The DHCP
      client sends out the constructed DHCPv6 message to the  Well-Known multicast
      address, i.e. All_DHCP_Relay_Agents_and_Servers multicast address as is
      defined in <xref target="RFC3315"/>. The DHCP relay agent receiving the
      message handles the message as a normal DHCPv6 relay agent in Section 20.1
      of <xref target="RFC3315"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Relay Agent Behavior">
      <t>The DHCP relay agent will receive the DHCPv6 message containing
      DHCPv4 Message Option from the multicast interface. It then handles the
      message as a normal DHCPv6 relay agent as in Section 20.1 of <xref target="RFC3315"/>.
      In this method, DHCP client and server are capable of communicating with
      each other directly, which does not necessitate any changes in
      DHCPv6 relay agent behavior.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Server Behavior">
      <t>Server receives DHCPv6 packets from the Relay Agent or directly
      from the Client. If it finds that received packet comprises the
      DHCPv4 Message Option it unpacks the content of this option and
      processes it as a regular DHCPv4 packet. The exact way how the
      server processes the DHCPv4 packet received over DHCPv6 protocol
      is out of the scope of this document.
      </t>
    </section>
<!--
  </section>
 <section title="Method 2: DHCPv4 over IPv6">
    <section title="Client Behavior">
       <t>In this case, the client is enabled to send and receive
       DHCPv4 messages through IPv6 sessions. The IPv6 UDP packet that
       has a DHCPv4 message as its payload is called DHCPv4 over IPv6
       packet. The client should use the port 546 as the destination
       port, and the port 547 as the source port of each DHCPv4 over
       IPv6 packet. </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Relay Agent Behavior">

       <t>The relay agent should also send and receive DHCPv4 messages
       through IPv6 on the interface facing to the client. It should
       listen for DHCPv4 over IPv6 packets on port 546, and send
       DHCPv4 over IPv6 packets on port 547.</t>

       <t>When the relay agent receives a BOOTPREQUEST message (i.e.,
       DHCPDISCOVER, DHCPREQUEST, etc.), it constructs a new relay
       agent-forward message. It then copies the source IPv6 address
       from the header of the received DHCPv4 over IPv6 packet to the
       peer-address field of the relay agent-forward message. The
       relay agent copies the received BOOTPREQUEST message (excluding
       any IP or UDP headers) into the DHCPv4 Message option in the
       new message. It then forwards such a relay agent-forward
       message to the server.</t>

       <t>When the relay agent received a relay agent-relay message
       that includes the DHCPv4 Message option from the server, it
       should extract the DHCPv4 message from the DHCPv4 Message
       option of the message, and relay agent it to the address
       contained in the peer-address field of the relay agent-reply
       message.</t>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Server Behavior">
    <t>When a DHCPv6 server receives a valid DHCPv6 message, it checks
    for the presence of a DHCPv4 Message Option. If it is not present,
    the server handles the DHCPv6 packet as is defined in <xref target="RFC3315"/>.
    If it is present, the server processes the payload of the option as a DHCPv4
    message. The DHCPv4 message is handled by the DHCPv6 server itself
    (most likely scenario) or forwarded to another DHCPv4 server.</t>

    <t>When sending out a DHCPv4 reply message, the DHCPv6 server MUST include a DHCPv4 Message Option in an encapsulating DHCPv6 message that contains the DHCPv4 message as the option payload.
    </t>

    <t>DHCPv4 messages with the same transaction ID SHOULD NOT be
    transported inside DHCPv6 messages with different transaction
    IDs.</t>

  </section>
-->
</middle>

<back>

  <references title="Normative References">
    &rfc2131;
    &rfc3315;
  </references>

  <references title="Informative References">
    <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-dhcpv4-over-ipv6" ?>
  </references>

</back>
</rfc>

